Doom. To many it's timeless. To imagine
a world without DOOM is to imagine a
world without first person shooters. It's
one of the most beloved series in the
history of video games, and the studio
that created it id Software, one of the
most prolific. There's an aura of mythos
around id Software - the creators of
a genre, the masters of DOOM. The history of
its founding fathers has been told over
and over again and with an early catalog
including names like Wolfenstein, Doom
and Quake it's clear to see why. There was
a rock and roll style to those early
days of id that captured the adoration
of nineties gamers. Romero's hair the
ferrari 328, the Congressional hearings.
It painted the picture of a
larger-than-life studio full of young
men defining culture and doing so by
breaking all the rules. But those days
are gone, ghosts that both define and
haunt the identity of modern id. And in
recent years as more of the founding
fathers left for different shores the
studio's identity in the public
consciousness has faded. One of the
reasons for this is the recent blind
spot in the history of id software, one
that stretches from the release of Rage
all the way to now. A time when the
studio went through some of its hardest
days, a failed sequel, a buyout, an
internal power struggle. But to the
surprise of everyone the punchline of
this uncertain era was an incredibly
confident game. A refreshing take on an
old idea that seemed to do something
that many had assumed was beyond the
ability of id. To reflect its history
through a modern mirror, to marry the old
and the new. The story of how DOOM 2016
came to be is a rather messy one, so to
tell properly we spend two full days
at the studio interviewing the people behind
its various iterations. The goal was to
tell the story of not only how this game
was created, how they struke its self aware
tone and designed its combat chest. But
also to tell the story of what happened
for all those years.
So first we packed our bags to take a
trip straight to hell
Richardson, Texas
From a gameplay feel perspective we reference DOOM 1 and DOOM 2
you know in the dorms everybody was playing DOOM
Diving in for hours at the time
It was awesome. Everybody loved DOOM. They thought it was bad ass
Again the movement, the no reloading they
the no taking cover, those are all
fundamental elements of doom 1
and DOOM 2
I started with id back in 91 and
working on Wolfenstein 3d and then
we moved onto Spear of Destiny the
sequel to wolfenstein 3d and then onto
the DOOMs and the various Quakes
started off actually doing some of the
page layout stuff and then also doing
some of the art for wolfenstein and
then for a long time it was just Adrian and I
doing the art. The roles varied from
time to time, I moved up to creative
director on some projects, producer on
others but I still consider myself
primarily an artist. [new voice] I joined as an
employee in 1998 had done contract work
for maybe a year or two years prior to that
I had taken the editor that John had
written and basically, making
it usable for Quake 3. When i joined
as an employee effectively that was
towards the end of Quake 3 and we
moved kind of immediately into Team
Arena. In addition to the editor
stuff started doing gameplay and
just kind of everything because you know
there was 3 or 4 programmers
at best self so we all did a lot.
[new voice] It wasn't the necessarily the earliest days
of id but it was it was some pretty
early days, back working on
Quake 2, back when the company was just
10 people or so. It wasn't like anything
else and just had a ball.
Really, really enjoyed it
and worked through Quake 2, the mission
packs, the console versions of Quake 2.
Quake 3 Arena. was the producer on
that. it was very small.
it was the kind of place where almost
anybody in the studio would be a lead or
director at another studio.
It was interesting there
was just kind of a mystique to it.
You had that the plan files
online and that was kind of how people
would follow the company, or the musings
of the of the people who
kind of become celebrities.
The personalities within the company very
much defined
the company and you can see those
fingerprints in the games.
There was a bit of the reverence
and an attitude that you didn't see
in a lot of other games. It didn't feel
corporate at all and certainly when you
showed up at the offices it didn't feel
corporate  at all.
We were kind of known for being that crazy video
game developer in that big black cube
out on the freeway in Mesquite Texas and
you'd ride up the elevators and get to
the sixth floor and there was a sign up
front that said id Software - suits 666
and you'd walk in and meet Miss
Donna. The long
time id mom, she's been here more than 20
years but she sat at a desk with a
with a massive demon image behind
her. It was fun you know it was
fun to go down and visit and and
as much as I never believed growing
up in Colorado and then living
in LA that I would never move to
Texas, when they offered the job
it was like yeah - this is an
opportunity of a lifetime. And 17
years later it's still where I love to come
When Marty joined id the team had just
started working on the expansion pack
for Quake 3 - Team Arena. A game that
was spawned from the studio's addiction
two Quake 3's capture the flag.
There's a group of us that played it
I don't remember which map it was - the space map with
the really short things, with the bfg
up here. And we played that 2vs2 CTF
every day at five o'clock for probably
three straight years. I mean I'm not kidding
every day and he we called it
MOTU - master of the universe. Whichever
team won was current MOTU and it was
some of the best times we had
because we were still tiny like you know
10 to 20 people. Yeah really fun a
lot of screaming and yelling and cursing
and tons of fun. [interviewer] I was saying to Tim (Willits)
that's probably the fastest capture
the flag in video game history.
You can do it like, four seconds?
Yes it really is so you know playing that
often with the same teams when everybody
had their strategies
sometimes matches would be over just
super fast but it was super fun. A lot of
good memories.
After Team Arena the team moved on to DOOM 3, a game that took
the series in a more narrative direction.
That had the player fighting demons in
beautifully lit but often
claustrophobic corridors. The game found
an audience but many felt that it
sacrificed gameplay in search of
breaking new technical ground.
Robert Duffy was lead programmer on the
project a game designed by a shockingly
small team by modern standards.
I think we finished DOOM with around 19
people in the studio maybe low twenties
but it was mostly built by fifteen,
sixteen, seventeen, eighteen people
something like that. I like a lot of the
effects that that we did
Imps spawning in and we had the ability
to tie lighting to sound
amplitude.
It was the level of
craftsmanship that I think that we put
in the game. As a studio you know we were
honestly too obsessive with quality i
think - every pipe had
to connect up and the
whole driving force behind
the studio was quality and polish
A really fun project
[interviewer] it's interesting how when people
talk about DOOM 2016 they go
"Oh it's just like DOOM 1 &amp; 2" but in terms of
environments and structure
it's actually got a lot of similarities with DOOM 3
Yeah i mean the UAC,
the kind of heavy industrial feel
We do reference probably more
from a gameplay feel perspective
we reference DOOM 1 and DOOM 2
again the movement, the no reloading, the
no taking cover those are
fundamental elements of DOOM 1 and 2
DOOM three did a lot to develop UAC
as that evil corporation
it had a a weighty
oppressiveness to it in an
interesting way. It's still
one of my favorite games that we made.
After DOOM 3 we had started another
project that internally we called
"Darkness". We worked on that a year maybe a
year and a half and just kind of
figured - we weren't feeling it? You know?
As a studio we were still
independent and so we had
the flexibility and the freedom to just
say that this isn't
working out.
And then Tim walked
into my office one day and he was
like "big machines and"
"apocalyptic setting" and you know all
this crazy stuff and so that was
kind of how RAGE started.
RAGE was a brand new venture for id utilizing John Carmack's
impressive megatexture technology it
depicted a vivid mad max-style world.
One full of areas to explore cities full of
people to talk to and even cars to drive
[Robert] It was certainly different than what we
had done - the wastelands were
kind of built in pieces for some
technology reasons but that was one of
the proving grounds.
It was one of the areas where megatexture
really shined and especially the ability
to stamp on it and kind of unique
everything up. Vehicle combat was
certainly challenging I think it's
challenging for most people that do it
to get it right and to keep a
shooter feel but yeah the outdoor areas
specifically on the
360 and ps3 - that much
visual fidelity, 60 Hertz we push
a lot of triangles to the engine so
there's a lot of lot of design art and
and technical challenges in RAGE.
RAGE wasn't the only project id was working
on John Carmack had hinted that DOOM 4
was in development at quakecon 2007 and the
game was officially announced to be in
production the following May. Then CEO
Todd Hollenshead suggested it played hommage
to DOOM 2 as I was set on earth during
a hellish invasion. In June of 2009
Zenimax Media the owners of Bethesda
Softworks acquired id software and
its intellectual property. But still no
images videos or teasers of the game
ever surfaced. Even after RAGE was
finished in 2011 and Carmack insisted
that even more resources would be put
towards the DOOM project. In fact over
the next few years the public was sent
mixed messages over the state of the
game's development.
[Marty] So the way we were  kind of structured for a while in the
late 2000s was we had a
team that was working on RAGE,
Tim was directing that. We had a team
that was working on DOOM - the kind of
campaign version - the past generation
of it. I was kind of leading a team of
multiplayer developers that were...
...we had done Quake Live and we'd moved
into DOOM development.
And that team finished RAGE
and we were big
We had finished DOOM with 19 people and
we were at a point where we had
almost 3 full teams so we were pretty large
a lot of growing - typical stuff
every company talks about when
they grow the kind of communication and
and all those kinds of things that come
into play. So there was kind of this moment
after RAGE where I started
looking a bit more at DOOM and you
again like a long kind of a long period
of evaluation and adjustment
[Danny] The period that followed was a rather
caustic one for the studio and DOOM 4
one of its many victims. So it's
understandable that id have never really
talked about the game. For years DOOM 4
was the elephant in the room that id
never spoke about and as a result the
conversation around this game has been
dominated by a leaked CG trailer and a
2013 kotaku article that painted the
picture of a heavily scripted
military-style shooter. So much so that
rumor mill articles and message board
conversations often referred to this
project as "Call of DOOM". But are so many
lingering questions, what was DOOM 4?
How did it play? How had it informed the 2016 version?
I was worried that many of the
answers to these questions would be lost
to time with all the recent departures
but as it turns out the creative
lead on the project was none other than
id veteran Kevin Cloud
So I would say what we had done is we had
explored a direction and got
to a certain point and felt like this
wasn't really capturing what we
felt like was DOOM - was going to be
a strong DOOM and what the fans
would want from it.
[Marty]  You mentioned the term "Call of DOOM"
that has been thrown around. It was
much closer to something
like that type of game. A lot more
cinematic lot more lot more story to it
a lot more characters around you and
that you are with throughout the
course of the gameplay. Definitely
different setting - it took place
on earth you know
[new voice] Robert Zemeckis-y, Contact, kind of like
"if this really happened" -  now granted just
want to be clear - it was awesome. But it was
more realistic. It was more
about the the the global impact of
a hellish invasion.
[Marty] Unbelievable production value - it was really
good from that perspective but it
was definitely a twist on DOOM that
took it into a much more cinematic,
much more scripted type of experiences.
It was a reimagining of doom in a
way that was new. I mean it was
totally new. When you were taking
cover and you're popping up and shooting
shooting enemies. The  demons looked a
lot different
it took awhile to get into
actually fighting demons - you were
fighting a lot of zombie type
creatures early in the game.
[Kevin]  As far as the upper level creative
direction of that, it was me
driving that and honestly again,
taking in a direction that I didn't think that
ultimately the fans would have enjoyed.
as far as a DOOM fan. Just trying to
get more character interaction a
little bit more connection to the world.
[Hugo] As a concept i can see why they
went there because I would probably want
to explore that too if it wasn't a DOOM game.
Because to tell
a bigger story it sacrificed the
Doom Slayer and DOOM is about one guy
involved in big things and DOOM 4 classic
was more about the big things.
[Kevin] It kind of comes off like that idea you
talked about earlier. About how you
had the pinky right - You said you had a vision of
redoing the the pinky in doom 3
and in this new doom
they're very different but to me they
both felt valid. right? And i think what
ultimately happened is that
I was kind of taking it in -I'm not
going to say DOOM 3 direction it
definitely wasn't that - but
conceptually I was taking it
off path and went too far in that path.
[interviewer] So I guess what was the sort of
impetus to stop it?
You know there's there's always
a thousand conversations
that go into some something like that
The biggest i think was that...
...I guess the best way to say it is it
didn't it didn't feel as much like DOOM
as I think a lot of us expected it to be
or hoped it would feel. It all boils down
to kind of feel and I give
Bethesda a lot of credit for sticking
with us through those decisions because
it takes a lot to stand by a
developer saying it just
doesn't feel right
[Kevin] Very tough I have to say. For me
personally very tough time
but you know in hindsight I think that
the studio and Zenimax
made wise decisions and ultimately
I loved DOOM, right? So I want to make sure
that it goes out every time as
something that the fans love.
There was actually a period of time
between the end of 2011, the
end of 2012, and right at the beginning
2013 where we kind of did
2 reboots or kind
of a rolling reboot of sort.
Took a step back and re-examined what we
consider to be the fundamental elements
of a DOOM game.
We asked Todd Vaughn who's the VP of Product Development at
Bethesda from the publishing perspective
To come down and spend some time with
us. I think we were we were struggling
with an unwieldyness
of how big the company was
and some focus issues.
There's a lot of stuff involved when you
when you go through that process and I
would say one of the big changes coming
out of that was we need to
refocus the studio just on one project.
[Danny] In the years that followed the
team was shaken up. Todd Hollenshead and
John Carmack left the studio. Carmack now
works for Oculus and is currently in
litigation with id parent company
ZeniMax over an IP dispute.
[Marty] Change is never easy for some people
you always go through that kind of stuff
when you're changing. We had
people who didn't agree and left.
We had other people that
didn't agree and we let go.
For some it's it's empowering and for
others its demoralizing but it's just
what you go through.
It's like any kind of big
change in life or if you've ever
been part of a team
I use sports analogies all the time
if you're part of
the Broncos and they go from
one type of defense to another type of
Defense you know? It's like "I don't
"like playing in the 4-3 I like the 3-4" so
I'm going to be upset about it
Or you can embrace it and just be like
yeah I understand we've got
this level of expertise and we want to
head in this direction and
we're gonna do it/
[Danny] The team was also bolstered by new blood
Hugo Martin who had previously worked at
Naughty Dog was responsible for
designing the jaegers for Guillermo del
Toro's Pacific Rim came on as creative
director while Crytek's former
graphics engineer Thiago Souza came on
board as lead renderer programmer
[Robert] When we first rebooted
this version of DOOM with Marty leading the
project I certainly worked with him on the
original pillars. The multiplayer.
campaign. Snapmap pillars and obviously
always involved in tech. We were starting
to assemble the tech team came from
programmers from both RAGE and the
prior DOOM project and then
Hugo came on board and
at that time Marty and hugo
really started running with the
game side of things and my focus
really turned largely on technology and
the engine team and
figuring out how the
hell are we gonna hit 60 on the console
[Danny] That's a three-year problems to worry about
Yes, but it was a lot of fun, a lot of
good collaboration
[Danny] It's been long assumed that once the team started work
on rebooting DOOM they left all the old
work on the cutting-room floor but one
of the gameplay pillars of DOOM 2016,
the glory kills, finds its origins in
what the team referred to as DOOM 4 1.0
[Marty] No matter where you're at you're
always a collection of
everything that's happened before you so
it's been it's been said
that we looked at
this game and then we scrapped it and
you know we decided to do this and
that's a nice sound bite but there were
definitely things
that... I'll give you an example
The previous iteration had a kind
of a sync melee system
where when you got
close to an enemy you'd end
up in a synced animation melee
type of system that resulted in a really
cool death of the enemy.
You initiate this syncing of the
you with the enemy and then this
animation plays out. You would look at
that and think of glory kills you know?
But it was slow it was a
very deliberate, very cinematic way of
approaching that.
Even pre-full-reboot we've had some
meeting where we were like "you know this is cool"
It's just slow. Can we
make it a little bit more like
fruit ninja with demons?
Where these things are fast
The animators developed this animatic taking
the work and the ideas that had been
done there. The idea that came out
of this is push forward combat and so
they did this animatic of push
forward combat and the initiation of glory kills.
[Kevin] The thing that really excited me
about it is when we first started seeing
the glory kill system come together. Kind
of redefined first-person combat for me
really started driving it closer.
We had an iteration of that in the
previous game but I think
Marty and animation team and Hugo
really work together to come up with
something very intense and exciting for that.
So it was pretty cool to see that
come together and I think for me
personally that really energized the
project for me.
And again, that was a good
moment but it was to a great extent
built on a knowledge base that had built
up through the course of developing the
the first version of it.
[Danny] So let's dive into some of that stuff
What ended up being
what DOOM is.
The first time you showed it I remember
obviously behind closed doors at
Quakecon. First of all, how do you end up
putting hundreds of people in the room
who don't end up leaking it?
I don't know. You know what?
We will give you
some of the footage
so you can see. We have it. It's never
been seen before.
QuakeCon I always refer to as the
greatest home-field advantage
in the history of games. Almost our
entire team at the time was in the
audience. I always say how lucky I am to be
able to be the one to stand
up and in front of an audience and
present the game whether it's at QuakeCon
or E3. I am only a representation of
the people on the team
that even this here
I'm just I'm just trying to do my best to
represent the team we have here
I got to represent a team that was all
sitting in the audience and then say you
know what you guys? You just want to see the game?
And we're sharing this just with you. Tim just mention that we turned off
the twitch TV. This is just for you
we have a lot to share with everybody
outside of this room at a later date but
we want this to be special and just like
we want this to be special for you
we want the first taste of DOOM for
everybody else to be special, too. So i
would like to make sure that everybody turns
off their recording devices
Put those cell phones in your
pocket. Camcorders down. Take off the
Google Glass. Google Glass freaks your
friends out anyway.
As much as I want you to understand our
approach to DOOM combat. Talking about
it really just doesn't do it a lot of justice.
[applause]
So you know where this is headed right?
The pictures are great but I
figured you guys
would like to see a
little bit of the game right?
That's great I think you like it! Awesome.
People refer to that as
the best moment of their careers.
You can have all the confidence in the world
in what you're doing but you just never
quite know what the response is
going to be. But to have a
big audience just cheer is the best
gratification in the world
I don't think there really any accidents I think that
we built what we felt was
really good. We thought that it paid
tribute to the original DOOMs and we
thought it looked amazing and ran great
and we just hoped that
players worldwide would think the same.
That was the story of how DOOM was rescued from the
depths of development hell but there's a
lot more to this tale. Tomorrow we
investigate how DOOM found its wonderful
self aware voice and the challenges of
making the right first impression
see you then
That doesn't mean that the game is dumb
because I think it's deceptively smart
and sophisticated it's just
easy to understand which is honestly how
things should be. I always compare it to
Apple products. pple when it's
at its best -
my son is six he knows how to use an
iPad you know that's that's good design.
Yet that thing is obviously pretty sophisticated
[Danny] Has your son played DOOM?
I don't know if i should say that on
camera
[Danny]  Well we know the answer then
He may or may not have played DOOM
He may have made it
to Foundry.
He might be struggling with the shield guys
and his mother might be extremely upset about it.
this could be an ongoing problem in my house.