It wasn't necessarily the earliest days
of id, but it was some pretty early days.
You know back working on Quake 2
back when the company was just
10 people or so
[new male voice] I started with it back in 91
working on Wolfenstein 3d
[new male voice] When I joined as an employee effectively that was
towards the end of Quake 3 you know
there was three or four programmers
at best. So we all did a lot
[First Voice] You'd ride up the elevators and get to
the sixth floor and there was a sign
out front that said "id Software - Suite 666"
It was what you would hope. Everybody loved
what they did. Pushing the envelope
in almost every single way
From a gameplay feel perspective we
reference DOOM 1 and DOOM 2
[new male voice] It had to be fast because that was a core element of
DOOM - you felt fast
You'd look at the sprites going *vomit* and like...
You know what I mean?
Like, have you seen the stuff that
goes on in DOOM?
We would play a game and  I'm thinking "We could do anything!"
It was DOOM but something else
[new male voice] Robert Zemeckis-y "Contact" kind of...
....the global impact of a hellish invasion
[new male voice] Very tough i have to say for me personally
very tough, tough time
A lot of money is spent when you make something and
then you decide to move away from it so
we have to do this...we have to do this
and it has been great!
Our asses were out there, but why not? I'd rather go down
swinging for the fences than bunting.
You can be really self-aware and make it work
[new male voice] Because you're expecting
the game to be like "Maybe it's a cult...
"...and it's a secret and no one knows"
But how about as soon as you walk in
it's playing on a fucking megaphone like
"We need volunteers for the Revenant"
"Program. We're going to turn people into Demons!"
When it finally went into the box
we were like "Don't breathe on it!"
"It works....don't even look at it!"