So we were like oh the demons...well you land"
on Mars and you don't know it's demon  yet
and then you find out it's demons
and oh my god! and somebody even asks
"What do you think they are?"
and they're like "I think they're demons" you know?
*interviewer laughing*
That's what we did, we laughed!
Because we were like "That is ridiculous" You know? Who cares?
"They have pointy teeth...they might be vampires..."
And then you'd find our they
murdered someone or they took
something away from you, and all of it was
like oh my god...who cares?
The phrase "demonic invasion in progress"
is meant to.....we're saying
something to the audience were literally
handing them a ticket for a train
ride and saying "are you ready to go?"
Because we're going we're going to leave right now!